Finding Aid for Joyce Lindeman Papers 1950-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Joyce Lindeman papers 1950-1997, 1955-1986
Lindeman, Joyce.
8 linear feet
9834 Aa 2
Associate professor of kinesiology and coach of the synchronized swimming team at the University of Michigan and national officer in United States Synchronized Swimming. Material relating to the Michifish Swim Club and the synchronized swimming team both as a club sport and varsity sport. Records include meeting agendas and minutes, budget and fundraising files, publicity materials, meet information and results, correspondence, photographs, and motion pictures.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers of Joyce Lindeman (donor no. 8657 ) were received in 1997. An additional accession was received in 2010
The collection is open for research.
No further additions to the records are expected.
Joyce Lindeman is best known as an associate professor of kinesiology at the University of Michigan and nationally recognized synchronized swimming coach and advocate. She received her B. S. in 1954 from Eastern Michigan University. From 1954 to 1965 she taught and coached synchronized swimming at Lee M. Thurston High School. After eleven years at Thurston, Lindeman returned to school to pursue an
M. S. degree at the University of Michigan. After completing her degree in 1966, Lindeman became an Assistant Professor at Western Michigan University.
In 1967 Lindeman returned to the University of Michigan as an Assistant Professor in the Department of Physical Education, then administratively housed within the School of Education. Her career at the University included a distinguished record of teaching and service. She was promoted to Associate Professor in 1973, and served as chairperson of the Department of Sports Management and Communication from 1989 to 2000. She also served as Associate Director of Curriculum and Instruction for the Division of Kinesiology from 1991 to 2000. In 1990 she was recognized by the State of Michigan's Teaching Excellence Fund and the University of Michigan for outstanding teaching.
In addition to her academic and administrative positions, Lindeman also coached the University of Michigan Synchronized Swimming team from 1972 to 1983. The Synchronized Swimming program was started at the University of Michigan in 1955 with the establishment of the Michifish Swim Club. The men and women of Michifish presented a yearly performance and participated in various competitions held throughout the nation.
Lindeman became the team's coach in 1972, and, in 1974, women's synchronized swimming was given varsity status, necessitating a split of the women's varsity team and the Michifish. Throughout the end of the 1970s, the women's varsity synchronized swimming team excelled, attracting top-notch swimmers such as Broderick Award winner Ruth Pickett. The team was well on its way to unseating number one Ohio State University as the reigning synchronized swimming team in the United States. Unfortunately, in 1982, synchronized swimming suddenly lost varsity status.
In 1982, the University of Michigan decided to participate in the National Collegiate Athletic Association's (NCAA) championships for women. Because the NCAA did not recognize synchronized swimming as a competitive sport, the University of Michigan revoked the synchronized swimming team's varsity status. Previously, the University sponsored championships through the National Association for Girls and Women's Sports (NAGWS). Despite petitions, a letter writing campaign, the inclusion of synchronized swimming as an Olympic sport, and compelling arguments by coaches and officials, the team was relabeled a club sport for the 1983-1984 season. Although the University followed through on scholarships that had already been awarded, it no longer provided the additional scholarships necessary for recruiting nor funding for expenses such as a coach's salary, equipment, and travel. Michifish continues to exist on campus as a club sport and presents a yearly watershow.
In addition to her work at the University of Michigan, Lindeman was active in many synchronized swimming organizations such as United States Synchronized Swimming Incorporated (USSSI), the American Alliance for Health, Physical Education, Recreation, and Dance, the National Synchronized Swimming Coaches Academy, the National Institute for Creative Aquatics, and the National Association for Girls and Women in Sport, as well as participating as a judge at synchronized swimming competitions. From 1984 to 1997, Lindeman served as vice president for Olympic international, administration, and education of USSSI. Her USSSI activities also included helping to develop a national training and certification program for synchronized swimming coaches. During this period she also coached and managed several national team tours to Europe and the Pan American Games, as well as the 1989 Olympic Festival and the 1990 Goodwill Games.
The Joyce Lindeman papers are divided into five series: Michifish, Topical Files, Varsity Teams, Department of Physical Education, United States Synchronized Swimming Incorporated, Photographs and Slides, and Motion Pictures. The contents chronicle the synchronized swimming team's promising rise from club to varsity status, and then the team's unexpected return to club status. The materials also document her work as a professor at the University of Michigan and her involvement in synchronized swimming at the national level.
Subjects:
Lindeman, Joyce.; Synchronized swimming.; Athletics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Women's Athletics.; Michifish.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Lindeman, Joyce.; Synchronized swimming.; Athletics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Women's Athletics.; Michifish.
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Michifish
  The Michifish series contains the earliest record of synchronized swimming at the University of Michigan beginning in 1955. The papers are organized alphabetically and contain information regarding the Michifish tryouts, training, watershows, and competitions. Information regarding competitions after 1975 will be found in the Varsity Team series.
  - Budget 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Choreography undated (Box 1)
  - Comedy Diving undated (Box 1)
  - Competitions
    - 1963-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1971 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions 1957-1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1973 (Box 1)
  - High School Clinic 1967 (Box 1)
  - Inventory undated (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes 1970 (Box 1)
  - Members 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1965 (Box 1)
  - Publicity 1955-1961 (Box 1)
  - Records undated (Box 1)
  - Selecting Members undated (Box 1)
  - Stunt Clinic 1968 (Box 1)
  - Theme Committee undated (Box 1)
  - Tickets 1970-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Training Program 1967 (Box 1)
  - Tryouts
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
  - Watershow Programs 1960-1982 (Box 1)
  - Watershows
    - 1961 (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 197 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  Papers unrelated to a specific team or event can be found alphabetically arranged in the Topical Files series. Most of the materials dealing with synchronized swimming associations, fundraising, and administrative duties are collected in this series, however, some additional information may also be housed in the Varsity Teams series. In addition, correspondence documenting the controversial change from varsity to club status is located in the correspondence folder labeled "Varsity to Club Change."
  - American Alliance for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance (AAHPERD) Convention 1997 (Box 1)
  - Alumni
    - Addresses, and Correspondence undated (Box 1)
    - Contributions 1979 (Box 1)
  - Amateur Athletic Union (AAU)
    - Coaches Certification Committee, Biomechanics 1980 (Box 1)
    - Eastern Solo and Duet Results 1979 (Box 1)
    - Indoor Results, Ohio State University 1979 (Box 1)
    - International Committee 1979 (Box 1)
    - Notes 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Aquatics Council 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (AIAW) 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Awards
    - All Americans 1977-1982 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1974-1981 (Box 1)
  - Big Ten Women's Athletic Departments 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Body Composition Testing
    - 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Charts and Signs for Meets undated (Box 1)
  - Coaching Publication Materials 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Code of Ethics 1978 (Box 1)
  - Collegiate National Championships 1996 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Coaches 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Education 1989-1993 (Box 1)
    - Fundraising, 1981-198, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Hendrix, Melissa 1981 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1971-198, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Publicity undated (Box 1)
    - Varsity/Michifish Separation 1974 (Box 1)
    - Varsity to Club Change 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Diet Materials 1968 (Box 1)
  - Effort to Reinstate Synchronized Swimming as a Varsity Sport (Box 2)
    - Gender Equity 1997 (Box 2)
    - Meeting and Memo 1995 (Box 2)
    - Presentation 1997 (Box 2)
    - Presentation Handouts 1997 (Box 2)
  - Federation International de Natation (FINA) 1981, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Forms
    - Audition undated (Box 2)
    - Scoring Sheets undated (Box 2)
    - Skill Testing undated (Box 2)
    - Weight Training undated (Box 2)
  - Instructor of Synchronized Swimming Course undated (Box 2)
  - Intercollegiate Reconstruction 1974 (Box 2)
  - Inventories 1978-1981 (Box 2)
  - Judges 1977-1980 (Box 2)
  - Lindeman Speech at UM Club 1981 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Synchronized News 1967-1978 (Box 2)
  - National Synchronized Swimming Coaches Academy (NSSC)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Synchro-Memo 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - National Institute for Creative Aquatics (NICA) 1973 (Box 2)
  - National Association for Girls and Women in Sport (NAGWS) 1977-1982 (Box 2)
  - News Clippings 1975-1980 (Box 2)
  - Olympics--Training Camp 1981 (Box 2)
  - Phone-a-Thon 1981 (Box 2)
  - Pool Reports 1970 (Box 2)
  - Swim-a-Thon
    - 1980 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
  - Training Materials
    - Articles undated (Box 2)
    - Bibliographies undated (Box 2)
    - Figures undated (Box 2)
    - Interval Training 1977 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous undated (Box 2)
    - Post Conditioning Program undated (Box 2)
    - Sculling undated (Box 2)
    - Summary of Work of the Committee to Study Major-Minor Deficiencies in Figures undated (Box 2)
    - Weight Program and Exercises undated (Box 2)
  - Trends in Synchro 1983 (Box 2)
  - United States Aquatic Sports (USAS) 1982 (Box 2)
  - United States Aquatic Sports (USAS) Convention 1980 (Box 2)
  - United States Olympic Committee (USOC) Conference Grant Program 1997 (Box 2)
  - Women's National Aquatics Forum 1976 (Box 2)
  - Workouts 1979-1982 (Box 2)
  - Workshops
    - Coaches Workshop 1977 (Box 2)
    - High School Clinic 1981 (Box 2)
- Varsity Teams
  Organized chronologically, the Varsity Teams series documents the activities of synchronized swimming team after it gained varsity status in 1974. Several years also include year-end reports that summarize each year's activities. Researchers desiring more detail can browse through many folders that give individual as well as team scores for each of the various competitions. Information concerning the budget, selection processes, and preparation for events hosted on the University of Michigan campus can also be found in this series.
  - 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Annual Report-Team Results (Box 3)
    - Budget (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - 1975-1976
    - Meet Results (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Regional Results (Box 3)
    - Year End Results (Box 3)
  - 1976-1977
    - Attendance Book (Box 3)
    - Budget (Box 3)
    - Michigan Invitational (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Nationals Materials (Box 3)
    - Team Materials (Box 3)
    - Western Illinois Meet (Box 3)
    - Year End Report (Box 3)
  - 1977-1978
    - Bowling Green Meet (Box 3)
    - Budget (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - MAIAW Regional Championship (Box 3)
    - Meet Materials (Box 3)
    - Meet Results (Box 3)
    - Michigan Invitational (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Oberlin/Ohio State University Meet (Box 3)
    - Ohio State University Meet (Box 3)
    - Recruiting (Box 3)
    - University of Arizona Meet (Box 3)
    - Team Suits (Box 3)
    - Year End Report (Box 3)
  - 1978-1979
    - Albany Swimming Championships (Box 3)
    - Bowling Green Meet (Box 3)
    - Financial Report (Box 3)
    - MAC Invitational (Box 3)
    - Northwestern Invitational (Box 3)
    - Pan American Results (Box 3)
    - Request for Equipment (Box 3)
    - Scholarship Money (Box 3)
    - Team Materials (Box 3)
    - University of Arizona Meet (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan Invitational (Box 3)
    - Western Michigan University Championships (Box 3)
  - 1979-1980
    - AIAW National Championships
      - Entries (Box 3)
      - Master Forms (Box 3)
      - Planning (Box 3)
      - Programs and Posters (Box 3)
      - Publicity (Box 3)
      - Results (Box 3)
    - Amateur Athletic Union (AAU) Materials (Box 3)
    - Budget (Box 3)
    - Housing, Tuition and Scholarships (Box 3)
    - Meet Results (Box 3)
    - Meet Schedules (Box 3)
    - Michigan Invitational Results (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Regional Championships at Ohio State University (Box 3)
    - Spanish Open
      - Fundraising (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Transportation/Equipment Requests/Memos (Box 3)
    - Tryout Materials (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan vs. Ohio State University Dual Meet (Box 3)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - AIAW National Championships (Box 4)
    - AIAW Operating Code (Box 4)
    - Budget (Box 4)
    - College Officials and Advisors (Box 4)
    - Meet Results (Box 4)
    - Michigan Open (January 24) (Box 4)
    - Michigan Open (March 1) (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Meets (Box 4)
    - National Team Trials (Box 4)
    - Skills Testing Information Sheets (Box 4)
    - Team Guidelines (Box 4)
    - Team Roster (Box 4)
    - Team Trials (Box 4)
    - Thank You Letters (Box 4)
  - 1981-1982
    - Correspondence re: Future of Synchronized Swimming at University of Michigan (Box 4)
    - Budget (Box 4)
    - Meet Results (Box 4)
    - Meet Schedule (Box 4)
    - Michigan Open (Box 4)
    - Northwestern Invitational (Box 4)
    - Recruiting (Box 4)
    - Regionals (Box 4)
    - Sandra Van Cauwenberg's Workout Binder (Box 4)
    - Synchro Team (Box 4)
    - Team Selection Materials (Box 4)
    - U.S.S.S. National Team Trials (Box 4)
  - 1982-1983
    - Meet Results (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - NAGWS-National Results (Box 4)
    - National Team Qualifiers (Box 4)
    - National Team Trials (Box 4)
    - Ohio State University Meet (Box 4)
    - Officials (Box 4)
    - Schedules (Box 4)
    - Team Expenses (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan Figure Meet (Box 4)
  - 1983-1984
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Team Rosters (Box 4)
- Photographs and Slides
  In the Photographs and Slides series, formal and informal photographs of the Michifish and varsity synchronized swim team give researchers a good idea of costuming and publicity since 1955. Unfortunately, most of the photographs are unidentified and the dates are only approximate.
  - 1955 (The Big Plunge) (Box 4)
  - 1955-1960 (Box 4)
  - 1955-1960 (Box 4)
  - 1960-1970 (Box 4)
  - 1960-1976 (Box 4)
  - 1971 (Myth or Miracle) (Box 4)
  - 1971-1975 (Slides) (Box 4)
  - 1973 (Box 4)
  - 1974-1981 (Box 4)
  - 1978-1979 (Varsity Swim Team) (Box 4)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - 1980 (Photos for AIAW Championship Program) (Box 4)
  - 1980 (Joyce Lindeman in Spain) (Box 4)
  - 1980-1981 (Varsity Team Pictures) (Box 4)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 4)
- Department of Physical Education
  The Department of Physical Education series is arranged alphabetically. The files contain material related to Joyce Lindeman's teaching and research activity in the department as well as general administrative files. The files include completed promotion review forms and teaching evaluations, instruction and curriculum materials, files related to Lindeman's Sea Grant research proposal, annual reports, meeting minutes, departmental goals and plans, and files related to Lindeman's own education.
  - General Administrative Files
    - Annual Report and Faculty Profiles 1979 (Box 5)
    - Appointment of Acting Chair 1976 (Box 5)
    - Dean Stark's Philosophy 1978 (Box 5)
    - Department Goals 1976 (Box 5)
    - Department Schedules 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - Education and Statistics Course Materials 1955-1966 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Faculty Meetings 1976 (Box 5)
    - Kinesiology Course Materials 1950-1952 (Box 5)
    - New Physical Education Program 1977 (Box 5)
    - Theft 1980 (Box 5)
    - White Committee Report on the Department of Physical Education 1976 (Box 5)
  - Promotion and Evaluation Files
    - B Form Summaries 1970-1976 (Box 5)
    - Department Evaluation 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    - School of Education Personal Yearly Report 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - Promotion Guidelines (Box 5)
    - Teaching Assistants 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - Teaching Evaluations 1974-1980 (Box 5)
    - Workload Formula 1969-1976 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - WSI Evaluations 1976 (Box 5)
  - Teaching and Research Files
    - Audio-Visual Instructional Materials 1966 (Box 5)
    - CPR Tests undated (Box 5)
    - Officiating Course 1973 (Box 5)
    - Script System 1979 (Box 5)
    - Scuba
      - Basic Scuba (PE 111) 1973 (Box 5)
      - Diving Institute 1975 (Box 5)
      - Proposals 1973 (Box 5)
      - Skin and Scuba Course Materials 1973 (Box 5)
      - Skin and Scuba Instructor Course (PE 114) 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    - Sea Grant Proposal 1976-1977 (Box 5)
    - Swim Classes 1974 (Box 5)
    - Swimming Curriculum 1968 (Box 5)
    - Teaching Schedules 1971-1972 (Box 5)
- United States Synchronized Swimming Incorporated
  United States Synchronized Swimming Incorporated, arranged alphabetically, documents Lindeman's involvement in synchronized swimming at the national level. The materials are particularly strong in documenting national level meets and efforts to improve synchronized swimming educational programs and coaching certification programs. These series includes convention materials, publicity, meeting minutes, agendas, budgets, meet information and results, special programs, and materials related to coaching certification at the national level.
  - Coaching Materials
    - ACE Program 1992-1997 (Box 5)
    - Certification Committee 1995-1997 (Box 5)
    - Certification Materials 1993-1995, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Certification Program (CCP) Task Force Materials 1996-2000 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Coaches and Judges 1993-1994 (Box 5)
    - Education/Certification Lessons 1996 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Orientation for Coaching Certification Program 1995 (Box 5)
    - National Coaches 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Training Design 1996 (Box 5)
  - Conventions
    - 1982 (Box 6)
    - 1985, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1995 (Box 6)
    - 1996 (Box 6)
    - 1997 (Box 6)
    - 2007 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - Donation Letters 1980-1985 (Box 6)
    - General Correspondence 1984-1986 (Box 6)
    - General Correspondence 1992-1999 (scattered) (Box 6)
  - Education Board
    - Education Board Agendas and Memos 1995-1996 (Box 6)
    - Prerequisite Courses 1995 (Box 6)
    - Vice President of Education Reports 1996-1997 (Box 6)
  - Financial Materials
    - Budget 1983 (Box 6)
    - Budget 1995 (Box 6)
    - Budget 1996-1997 (Box 6)
    - Budget Draft 1996-1997 (Box 6)
    - Education Budget 1995 (Box 6)
    - Markers Accounts 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - General Administrative Files
    - Ad. Hoc. Officials 1984 (Box 6)
    - Agenda and Option Plans 1984 (Box 6)
    - Application Forms, n. d. (Box 6)
    - Annual Report 1984 (Box 6)
    - Board of Directors 1984-1985 (Box 6)
    - Board of Directors 1996 (Box 6)
    - Board of Directors 1997, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Code of Conduct 1983 (Box 6)
    - Code of Ethics (Box 6)
    - College Relations 1984-1985 (Box 6)
    - Collegiate Development Steering Committee 1998-2000 (Box 6)
    - Committee Reports 1982-1984 (Box 6)
    - Competency Ideas 1996 (Box 6)
    - Credentials Report 1984 (Box 6)
    - Deadlines 1984-1985 (Box 6)
    - Expense Report Form 1985 (Box 6)
    - Form for Motions 1985 (Box 6)
    - High School Synchro Programs 1986 (Box 6)
    - "Incentives in Sport," Tracy Rehbein 1985 (Box 6)
    - Insurance 1985 (Box 6)
    - Logo Licensing Agreement, n. d. (Box 6)
    - Local Swimming Committee 1980 (Box 6)
    - Michigan and Ohio High School Athletic Association undated (Box 6)
    - National Team Materials 1981-1984 (Box 6)
    - NCAA Materials 1995-1996 (Box 6)
    - Newsletter Dates 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    - Overall Pool Time Requirement 1984 (Box 6)
    - Procedures for Judges Ratings 1985 (Box 6)
    - Reservations and Confirmations 1996-1997 (Box 6)
    - Rulebook 1986 (Box 6)
    - Rules and Regulations 1982 and n. d. (Box 6)
    - "Selecting a College and Synchronized Swimming Program," Joyce Lindeman, n. d. (Box 6)
    - Sports Medicine Committee 1981-1982 (Box 6)
    - Synchronized Swimming Articles undated (Box 7)
    - Team Managers Manual 1989 (Box 7)
    - Vice Presidents Planning Meeting 1997 (Box 7)
    - Yearbook 1985-1987 (Box 7)
    - United States Olympic Committee (USOC) Markers 1996-1997 (Box 7)
  - Meets
    - Junior National Indoor Championship 1980-1981 (Box 7)
    - Junior National Outdoor, Denver 1981 (Box 7)
    - Junior National and Midwest Zone Championships 1982 (Box 7)
    - Junior National Results and Qualifying Materials 1982 (Box 7)
    - Junior National Results 1983 (Box 7)
    - Meet Material and Results 1985-1986 (Box 7)
    - Midwest Zone Championships 1981 (Box 7)
    - Midwest Zone Championships 1982 (Box 7)
    - National Team Trials 1980 (Box 7)
    - National Team Trials 1981 (Box 7)
    - Results of Olympic Trials, Senior Nationals, and Board of Governors Meeting 1984 (Box 7)
    - Script for Opening and Closing Award Ceremonies, Intercollegiate Nationals 1985 (Box 7)
    - Senior Nationals 1981 (Box 7)
    - Sports Festival Materials 1979 (Box 7)
    - Sports Festival Materials 1981 (Box 7)
    - Sports Festival Materials 1983 (Box 7)
    - Sports Festival Materials 1983 (Box 7)
    - USSSI Championships 1980 (Box 7)
  - Publicity
    - 1982 (Box 7)
    - 1984 (Box 7)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 7)
  - Special Programs
    - Boys and Girls Clubs 1994-1995 (Box 7)
    - Camps and R&R Camps 1985 (Box 7)
    - Gender Equity 1992-1996, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Parks & Recreation Report 1989-1990 (Box 7)
    - Starting a Synchro Program 1988-1995 (scattered) (Box 7)
    - Synchronize 1985 (Box 7)
    - YMCA Training Program 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Motion Pictures
  Motion pictures of several competitions in the late 1960s and early 1970s also give an idea of the skill level of the University of Michigan swimmers. In a more recent film, award winner Ruth Pickett is shown in Figures for Degree of Difficulty Project which was produced in 1981. These motion pictures are in various formats which include Super 8 film, 8 mm film, and video tape. Included in this series are Don Canham's Champions on Film which are synchronized swimming training tapes produced on continuous running cartridges. It appears that University of Michigan synchronized swimming team members may have participated in the production of these tapes.
  - Continuous Running Cartridges